A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Bogota Files on the Southern Cone FA559
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Latin America and the Caribbean, Bogota Files on the Southern Cone
1973-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA559
2.62 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Primarily consists of correspondence, program management budgets, and associated materials.
Arrangement
As received.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation originally maintained an office in Bogota, Colombia from 1962 to 1982. After the Bogota office's closure in 1982, responsibility for Colombia programming was administered by other Latin American country offices focusing on the Andean Region and Southern Cone until 2016 when the Foundation established another office in Bogota.
The Ford Foundation started to explore possibilities for assisting programs in Colombia in 1960 in response to requests from Colombian universities. It made its first grants to the country in 1961, and then, in 1962, it established an office in Bogota. During the time of the first Bogota office, the Foundation's Colombia program primarily focused on supporting projects and initiatives involved with education, social sciences, science and technology, agriculture, and population. Within the first 14 years of the Colombia program's existence, the Foundation had spent almost $20.6 million in grants to the country (The Ford Foundation in Colombia, 1961-1974, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 9287-11774 (FA739D), Report 009501). At different times throughout its run, the first Bogota office was also responsible for administering the Foundation's Peru and Venezuela programs. It oversaw grants for both countries until 1965 when the Lima, Peru office was established and the Mexico City, Mexico office took over responsibility for the Venezuela program. The Bogota office resumed responsibility for the Venezuela program in 1972 after the Foundation closed its Caracas, Venezuela office.
The Ford Foundation closed the Bogota office in 1982. Regional responsibility for the Andean Region and Southern Cone was transferred to the Lima office. The Lima office administered the Foundation's Colombia program until 1991 when the Foundation then established the Andean Region and Southern Cone office in Santiago, Chile (The Ford Foundation: 40 Years in the Andean Region and Southern Cone, 2003, Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 13949-17726 (FA739F), Report 016928). The Santiago office oversaw the Foundation's support for Colombia until the Foundation opened a new Bogota office in 2016.
The current Andean Region office in Bogota oversees programming in Colombia and Peru.
- Academia de Humanismo Christiano, 1976 (Box 1)
- Chile -- Program Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
- Chile -- General Correspondence, 1974 (Box 1)
- Chile -- General Correspondence, 1975 (Box 1)
- Chile -- General (File I), 1976 January-June (Box 1)
- Chile -- General (File II), 1976 July-1977 January (Box 1)
- Curso de Capacitacion, 1973 (Box 1)
- Southern Cone -- Small Program Actions, 1974-1975 June (Box 1)
- Southern Cone -- Small Program Actions, 1975 July-November (Box 1)
- Southern Cone [CONFIDENTIAL], 1975 (Box 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted from scholarly access.
- Chile (1/2) [CONFIDENTIAL], 1973-1978 (Box 1)
- Chile (2/2) [CONFIDENTIAL], 1978-1980 (Box 1)
- Chile -- Security and Human Rights [CONFIDENTIAL], 1979 (Box 1)
- Buenos Aires -- Field Office Management, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
- Chile Programs, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
- Committee for Peace, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
- Richard W. Dye -- Personal, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
- Human Rights -- Correspondence/Memoranda, 1976 (Box 2)
- Regional Programs, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
- Santiago -- Field Office Management, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone -- Grant Management, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone -- Itineraries, Schedules and Meetings, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone -- Program Budgets, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone -- Program Management Budgets, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone -- Small Program Actions, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone -- Refugees, Dec 1973-Dec 1975 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone -- Refugees, 1976 (Box 2)
- World Council of Churches, 1976 (Box 2)
- Southern Cone [CONFIDENTIAL], 1976 (Box 2)